One of the themes that um and I try to
always at the end of each marker wizard
book typically talk about what the
unifying themes are, but it one that has
been true across all the books until
this last one and even for some traders
in this last one as well, but has been
looking for asymmetric trades. The the
secret of how these traders have done so
spectacularly well is one form or
another their trading methodology is
find situations where you can make
three, four, even 10 times what you're
risking on the trade. We got to see
these guys returns. They send us their
material to verify and some of the guys
that had the best sort of results. So
their monthly percentage returns are
just they're wild. you look at them and
you think, how did they have the
fortitude to to wake up and trade the
next month because it was a down 30 or
50% month
>> with the next generation here. Is was
there any interview in there that that
you think challenged your own kind of
beliefs or maybe thoughts at all? Yeah,
I mean the idea of shorting smaller cap
stocks as a way to get success would
certainly not have been on my list of on
my top 100 list of ways to [laughter]
market. But to succeed and what
ultimately happens in the process is
they find they love this thing and they
just it's like their work is their
hobby. It has to be that type of
attitude. If you're only in it, if doing
all that research is work, uh you're not
going to be you're not going to succeed
spectacularly.
>> One is they're they're usually pretty
self-aware. They understand who they are
and what they want. Two is they have
clear goals. They're not confused about
what they're trying to achieve. Three is
they believe in themselves. A lot of
times they believe in themselves when
there is no evidence to support that
belief whatsoever. Whether that's blown
up trading accounts or family members
telling them you're not good at this, go
do something else. Four is that they are
pretty independent as people. You're not
going to probably find them working a
nineto-five as a a cog in the machine.
Five, they're very passionate about
trading as we mentioned a minute or two
ago. Six, they're committed. They're
they're sticking with this through thick
or thin. So that leads to persistence.
They're all very persistent in achieving
their goals. Uh beyond that, they're
they're very willing to pursue their
dreams despite the fear of failure. So
they press on even if they're afraid
they might fail. and they really have an
ability to focus that you don't see so
much in everyday people.
>> What would your trading look like if
capital wasn't the constraint? That's
the reality for most traders. It's not
skill holding them back. It's size.
Trade the pool changes that. Step into
the US equity markets with up to
$200,000 in buying power without
committing your own capital. Full access
to stocks and ETFs, long or short,
executed with the precision and freedom
serious traders expect. Your performance
is measured by one standard. Disciplined
risk management and consistent
execution. Meet that standard and you
operate at scale. No subscriptions, no
ongoing obligations, just a clear path
forward. For those ready to trade beyond
limitations, this is the next level.
>> Markets, speculation, and risk. This is
the Chat with Traders podcast.
Welcome back to Chat with Traders.
Today's guests are Jack Schwagger and
George Coyle. Jack Schwagger is a
globally recognized authority on trading
and financial markets renowned for his
groundbreaking Market Wizard series
which has educated and inspired
generations of traders, investors, and
market professionals around the world
across titles including the original
market wizards, the new market wizards,
hedge fund market wizards, the unknown
market wizards, and now what's coming
next, the next generation market
wizards. So Jack's in-depth interviews
with elite performers have become
essential reading for anyone seeking to
better understand the art and science of
trading. His career has also included
senior industry roles such as partner at
Fortune Group, a London-based hedge fund
advisory firm, along with director of
futures research positions at several
major Wall Street firms. Jack is also no
stranger to chat with traders, having
previously joined us on episodes 27,778,
and 308, and it's a pleasure to welcome
him back onto the show. Well, joining
him today is co-author George Coyle.
George is the founder of Triangulated
Capital Management and brings more than
two decades of experience across hedge
funds, research firms, and family
offices in roles including chief
investment officer, portfolio manager,
systematic strategy designer, macro
strategist, and trader. George is widely
respected for his deep study of elite
traders, market history, and performance
psychology. Through his writings and
research, he has focused on identifying
the timeless principles, common
patterns, and decision-making frameworks
shared by exceptional traders across
generations. Together, Jack and George
have collaborated on Market Wizards: The
Next Generation, highlighting a new
generation of extraordinary traders and
the lessons they offer in today's
evolving markets. This is incredible.
Uh, welcome, Jack and George, to chat
with Traders. I got to pinch myself here
because I mean the market wizards books
these are this is timeless material.
This material lives on forever. So this
is incredible to have you both on.
Welcome to chat with traders.
>> Hey thanks for having us Kevin and maybe
you should be doing my PR going forward.
That was a pretty good introduction.
[laughter]
>> I appreciate it. So I want to just dive
straight in. How did this collaboration
happen?
>> Yeah. So um basically what happened was
we had a mutual acquaintance friend uh
Marit Sebert uh in Europe and uh I got a
email from Morates asking me would I be
willing to read an article from this
fellow who wrote an wrote an article
about Michael Marcus who was chapter one
>> of the first Marcus Wizards book and I
said well yeah sure send it to me and uh
I read it was pretty good and uh then I
got a guess I got a call from George, I
forget, but just asking to do a call and
I was more than happy to to accommodate
him of it because I had seen his work
and uh we had a we had a talk and George
was planning to do a book which he can
describe and uh that I had no intention
a no intention of uh doing another book
at that time nor any thought of working
with George and uh and I was just giving
him advice uh just my best advice. vice
and how to go and I even offered to
introduce him to my editor if you wanted
and and I'll let George take it from
there.
>> Yeah, I I said no to that offer
initially, which uh seems like a
bonehead move, but you know, at the time
I didn't really have a good idea for a
book. And fast forward about a year, I
was trying to get my business off the
ground and struggling like a lot of
people do. And so I started to study the
early careers of a lot of really really
successful people. So Warren Buffett for
example, he spent about three years as a
stock broker and didn't do very well at
it. Uh according to his biography and
then I found that John Bogle, you know,
the founder of Vanguard, the the most
popular investment strategy of all time,
which is lowcost, you know, passive
indexing in the S&P 500 essentially. It
took him eight years to get that going.
So, when I found all these stories, I
kept finding more and more great stories
and I said, "This would make a really
good book." Um, but I figured I would
use so much of Jack's material. And Jack
obviously is is uh very well known and
I'm not. So, I approached him and said,
"Hey, what if I wrote a book within the
Market Wizards universe that isn't a
traditional wizards book, but really
focuses on these early stories and uses
a lot of your material?" And ultimately,
um, through a series of steps, it
evolved into what it is now. So, a
traditional market wizards book.
>> Wow. I mean, that's just incredible.
And, you know, doing research for this
interview really what I came to find out
is it, you know, Jack, when you first
had started writing, your first book was
the complete guide to futures market.
You wrote that. By the way, I heard you
say by hand 800 pages.
>> Yeah.
>> Which these days you can click a mouse
and write 800 pages. I can't imagine
what that was like back then, but you
were trying to solve a problem is what
you said. and George, your principles of
great traders, you were trying to solve
a problem with that as well. So, it
almost really feels like the perfect
collaboration. It's not like you were
both trying to, you know, your goal
wasn't I'm to try to be famous, sell
millions of copies. The goal was really
I need a I have a problem I need to
solve. Is that accurate?
>> So, yeah, first of all, a complete god.
Congratulations on getting that right.
Everybody usually not everybody but most
people kind of think the first book was
market wisdom. It wasn't. It was a
complete guide. And I wrote that I took
us about it but I didn't think there was
a good market a good market good book on
futures markets.
>> This is back in 1983
and so I had an opportunity I took a
sbatical took a year so sbatical. So
this I mean PCs I think consistent
existed in their infancy but not really
not I wasn't using them. So everything
was by hand. Um I did use my secretary
from from a previous uh uh dire when I
was director futures research at at a
brokerage firm. So I used her to kind of
trans uh I would record stuff and send
it to her and she would type it up. So
that was done. But everything else like
charts I had to do by hand. Uh
and this was a book that was analytical.
So there was some you know math
involved. I remember literally doing
multiple regressions on a calc you know
by calculator which is really tedious uh
and very easy to make a mistake so you
got to be careful. Um anyway, so it it
it took a year uh working really
intensely uh morning night and my goal
was simply to write the best analytical
book on the futures markets at least at
that time and that was my and I wasn't I
want to emphasize this I wasn't trying
to write a book that would sell a lot of
copies because yeah
>> I don't know if this is my original
thought plot or I heard it somewhere
else but the the sales of a book are
inversely correlated to the number of
formulas and I was you know quite aware
of that and [clears throat]
uh but like I came to this I you're
doing fundamental analysis you have to
get into regression analysis and I
thought I was going to do one chapter
turned out well I couldn't started right
the first chapter well I can't do this
unless people understand basic
statistics so I have to write a chapter
on that and then I said well I can't
stop at simple regression I have to do
multiple regression then I you know and
on and on I ended up with six chapters
and god knows how many pages so I knew
the book wasn't geared for mass audience
ience just because it was it it was had
some an you know real analysis in it. So
um that wasn't my goal. I just wanted to
write the most thorough book.
>> And is that when market wizard stepped
in when you were like well actually I I
know some guys great traders and this
would be good for a large audience here.
>> That didn't happen that way. What
happened was I had no intention like I
said I took a year. It was a really
tense work. Uh so I wasn't planning to
write another book, but I did have the
idea um that gee, you know, I did know
some great traders like Marcus and Coner
and uh and I said, gee, it would
probably be a fun idea to go around the
country and interview the world's best,
you know, the country's best traders. Uh
but I was a research director. That's a
full-time job, more than full-time job.
So I didn't see I could do it. And I got
invited to lunch by a publisher, another
publisher, and they wanted me to do a
series of books. they they had seen the
complete guide and that did pretty well
for that type of book and they wanted me
to do a whole series of books, you know,
you know, a book on on gold anal gold
analysis, a book on grain analysis, just
different books on different types of
analysis. And I said, look, I've been
there, I've done it. I don't want to do
that again, but if I was ever going to
write another book, I mentioned this
market wizard idea and he said, great.
Why don't you do it? So that was the
catalyst. I didn't have the time, but I
did think it would be a fun thing to do
>> and so I agreed and I basically did it
on nights and weekends and uh
>> and got it done.
>> Did you know we would be where we are
today with now just a huge series? I
mean at any given time somebody's
reading a market wizards book. I mean
it's
>> never thought of doing a series. I was
just writing the you know this one book
market wizards. never thought of of
doing the additional ones at least not
before I wrote the first one but the
first one did extremely well and um I
knew more traders and I I certainly
didn't exhaust the idea so um a couple
few years later I decided to do I would
do another one and that was the new
market wizards and then after that like
every six or seven years
>> went back to it and did another one. Uh
so George, you've studied a lot of these
traders um that have been in the
original mark uh market wizards. Uh why
was there that sense of curiosity there?
What were you trying to solve in doing
that?
>> Why are we curious about the things
we're curious about? You know, that's a
that's a question we might not be able
to answer here, but specifically I was
designing trading systems. I mean, I had
always read the wizards books and had
always studied traders, but at one point
I was
>> designing systems and I had read the
work of Ed Sakod on his website over the
years. and started to see a lot of what
he said manifesting in the systems that
I was running in terms of well here's
what the back test says here's what you
actually got and that led me to just do
a deep dive on his website and I
aggregated everything I could over about
20 years of his information and I
categorized it and read it and it made a
lot of sense and I said well I don't
want to have to do this again so I'm
going to write this as a paper and I
started just writing sort of
categorically and here are the factors I
said this doesn't read very well so I'll
try to make it a Q&A and I wound up
doing that and sent it to him and he
published it on his website. It's still
there so people can can read it. But uh
once I did that I noticed that a lot of
the things that he said were inherent to
robust systems were the same things that
discretionary guys were saying about
their trading process. So Martin Zwig
had talked a lot about the trend as an
important factor in trading. Um and
Soros said the secret to his uh success
was correcting his mistakes which
essentially is cutting his losses. So I
said, "Boy, you know, there's so many
similarities. I'm going to pull this
string and see where it goes." And I
read a lot of books and articles and
went back to as far as I could really. I
wound up in, I guess, the late 1800s in
terms of of written work. And I just
aggregated all of that mainly because I
wanted to to use it to guide my process.
Um, but also so when I hit a draw down,
I'd have something to to go, you know,
drown my sorrows with essentially like
got to go back and do the right thing.
And then once that was done, I just I
started to enjoy doing it. I said, I've
always thought Soros is interesting.
Let's let's do him. And then Dr. Miller
and Marcus. So, you know, somebody read
the Marcus paper recently and said, why
did you do this? You know, this is still
seems like a ton of work, but I was just
genuinely curious um about his story for
one because it was such a great chapter,
but also just in how he did what he did.
For whatever reason, I'm just naturally
curious about how traders do what they
do. You know, that curiosity led you
here, though. I mean, for that person
that asked, "Why'd you do this? It was a
lot of work." Well, guess what? You're
co-authoring the Market Wizard's book
now because of that curiosity, right?
>> Yeah. And I think people have different
hobbies. You know, maybe mine are a
little strange, but I read trading
books. And for me, you know, when you
see a a piece of information in one book
and then something else in an article
and then something else in an interview
or what have you and you can put all
that together and combine it and come up
with sort of a larger message, it's like
solving a puzzle. I don't know. I I
enjoy it.
>> Well, you said you've you've aggregated
all this data. You've studied like
centuries of traders and you've come up
with a few commonalities. these three
core trading principles among great
traders is what you call them. What are
those three principles? And then Jack,
I'm curious if if you think those three
principles have applied to the next
generation um as well.
>> Uh so I'll go with the three there. Uh
respect the price action of the market,
your winning positions, and cut your
losing positions. So pretty simple, but
uh those are the three main things that
were consistent across a 100 plus years
of the grades. Well, well, I've heard
from Jack in a prior interview him
saying it's better to keep things
simplistic than complex. Is that right?
>> What are your thoughts?
>> It's um to a degree. I mean, it really
depends. Um I mean, if
keep things no more complex than they
need to be would be a better way of
putting it. Uh because sometimes
sometimes depending on the approach,
they need to be complex. So some of the
people I've interviewed in the course of
the books uh uh some famous quants like
D Shaw and Ned Thorp two brilliant minds
um they they were certainly highly
highly complex um but that was that was
the way that was their edge that was
their their methodology so I wouldn't
say you should never be complex and in
fact um when you get down to systems if
you go to systematic training I think
it's very difficult to just have a
simple system that is really
not that not a simple system that can't
make money but one that has really good
return to risk. I think it's difficult
to would be very difficult to do that in
a very simplistic fashion. Very simple
systems. They may make money over time
but to but with a lot of volatility and
risk and and to get really good return
to risk I don't think you can avoid some
degree of complexity.
>> Right. You know what I find fascinating
too is you've mentioned there's really
no single approach to the market. So
maybe with that too like some maybe
simple some complex some focus for
example fundamentals some technical some
scalp some day trading it's swing
trading you know it's there's so many
different approaches and I want to ask
you both too with that because the next
generation there are a few different
approaches as well in fact there was an
approach that we haven't seen yet in a
market wizards book. Is that correct?
>> Yeah. So you're you're you're quite
right on that. So one of the themes that
um and I try to always at the end of
each market wizard book typically talk
about what the unifying themes are but
it one that has been true across all the
books until this last one uh and even
for some traders in this last one as
well but has been uh looking for
asymmetric trades. The the secret of how
these traders have done so spectacularly
well is one form or another their
trading methodology is find situations
where you can make three, four, even 10
times what you're risking on the trade.
That's that's where they get their uh
really good performance because their
whole methodology is geared to when they
win they or they're looking for spots
and situations where they can win a lot
relative to the amount of risk required
to prove that trade is wrong. That in a
nutshell is the essence. Even for
traders with completely different
approaches, when you get down to it in
their own way, they're trying to do
that. They're trying to find the spot
where they can have an opportunity to
make as I said three, four, five, 10
times what they'll lose if they're wrong
on the trade. So, uh that is a big
unifying theme in this book. There were
few traders who at least at one point in
their career, usually the earlier part
did come up with methodologies where
they made their initial millions which
which really defied that. in fact was
just the opposite. They were doing they
were doing a strategy which
theoretically could lose multiples what
what they were could make and that was
specifically uh a few of these traders
started out by selling small cap uh
going short small cap stocks which I
mean the best you can do is it goes to
zero and some of these small cap stocks
when they're in these pump and dump
phases they could go to extreme extreme
levels I mean not
unheard of for them to go up a thousand%
in a day even. So there is there is a
lot of risk there and a limited
potential. So yet they made it work and
we could talk about how they made it
work but uh so you have that and you
also had one trader who
second half of his career went uh a
large part of his trading was uh
shorting options. And shorting options
is the kind of poster child for a uh uh
you know the the old phrase is what
picking up nickels in front of a
bulldozer. Um you you you know there if
you see the if you see the charts the
equity charts of traders who sell out of
the money options pretty much looks like
an mountain chart until they step on a
mine otherwise known as a sharp quick
selloff in the market. Um and and it all
evaporates because that type of strategy
the more the market the market
volatility starts going up the more it
goes up your your position not only you
losing your your the key is not that
you're losing on your position is your
position grows exponentially larger as
as the market in this case volatility
moves against you. So it's it's a
radically uh opposite uh type of
strategy. Uh again he made it work very
well and but he had ways of controlling
the risk and characteristics
how he made that work without stepping
on the landmines.
>> Yeah those landmines seem inevitable.
You know there there's maybe one or two
in the field. I was George I heard you
say that in an interview. There might
you know the field might be pretty clear
and empty for the most part but one or
two are kind of sitting out there. It's
going to it may happen at one point. So
certainly risk has to be managed. But
George, how important do you think it is
to that your trading system or strategy
needs to be congruent with who you are
like your personality? Uh because again,
there were a lot of different traders in
the book. In fact, I interviewed your
oldest um next generation market. He's
not going to like I said that. Uh I
think he's only 40. You're only 40,
Jason. Uh but what he would say too, I
mean he was Mr. Consistent in the book,
right? Mr. Consistency and then you had
those that were shorting the small caps,
you know, as well. So there's so many
different paths. There's no singular
path. But how important is it, George,
that it remain consistent with your
personality?
>> Well, I think it's very important, but I
I think there's shades of gray, right?
inherently as people with with very few
exceptions, we want to
>> buy something cheap and sell it dear,
right? I I think most people including
myself come to the markets and say,
"Well, that stock's too expensive. I'll
wait till it gets cheaper. That stock's
too pricey. I'll short it because it's
going to go down." And that tends to be
wrong. So, I think it was Bill Eckard in
New Market Wizards who said something to
the effect of
average human tendencies are not good
for trading. Um, and I think that's
true. So, in some sense, I think what
would make any of us comfortable would
not lead to profits potentially long
term. Now, that said, I think within
that, there are a lot of, as you said,
uh, Kevin, ways to succeed and ways to
peel the onion, and I think you need to
find what works for you in terms of
personality,
um, within that. And so, for example,
some guys like to day trade. they can't
stand holding positions and allowing
unrealized losses or or big changes in
equity. Other guys think day trading
sounds absolutely miserable. Uh we
interviewed one guy uh for actually a
book that's going to be coming up, but
he more or less said that nobody could
pay him enough money in the world to
spend his life in front of a screen. So
you've got sort of diametrically opposed
views on that. And I think that people
need to find within the reality that
what they're doing is probably not going
to be comfortable. They need to find
relative comfort within the discomfort.
Otherwise, it just won't work.
>> Yeah. I believe Michael Marcus even said
that you if you try to combine two
traders, even if they're highly
successful, but you try to combine two,
you're going to get the worst of both of
them. Well, I wonder why do why do you
think that is, Jack?
>> Yeah. Um because everybody has their own
psychological makeup and what they're
comfortable and beliefs and what they're
comfortable with. So I mean if I think
back to that first book you have uh you
have uh Jim Rogers I ask him about uh uh
whether he ever looks at charts because
he's such a pure fundamentalist. He says
well if you mean like to look at the
history of where it's been. Yeah. But do
I believe in any of this head and
shoulders mumbo jumbo whatever you know
term he used I forget the exact phrase
it's all a bunch of nonsense and says
then he says the only uh I never met a
rich technician except those that sell
their services. So that's his cynical
view of tech of of technical analysis.
Then you get somebody like Marty Schwarz
who who was on the fundamental side for
over a decade, lost money in his
trading, I think he said every year,
turned to chart analysis and became
spectacularly successful. Um, and so,
uh, you know, and he he talks about
people, not that I mentioned my
interview with Rogers, but he talks
about that. Yeah, I think somewhere in
the interview he says something like,
uh, uh, you know, people who criticize
chart analysis and what, you know, what
what a stupid attitude. I mean, I grew
rich as a technician. So, you've got,
you couldn't be more different. So,
they're core beliefs. Jim Rogers if he
if he went to explore Charles and he
could never be successful because he's
such built-in cynical attitude towards
it and and Schwarz just whatever it is
about it fundamental analysis didn't
work for him but but technical analysis
>> you everybody has their own kind of
thing and also in terms of risk you've
got in this upcoming book uh you've got
one fellow well like one who one of the
guys who never had a losing month or at
least not back. Well, we could we could
verify 11 years and before that he was
with a prop firm, not a prop firm, a
family office. He still hadn't didn't
have losing months, but we couldn't
verify that. But any case, just every
month he makes money. Uh, but he his
really he is so riskaverse. I mean,
forget about having a losing month,
which he never had. I mean, for him a
losing day is a really, you know,
hopefully rarish event. So, um, you have
that attitude. Then you have people who
a couple of people in the book who kind
of went from a accounts relatively small
accounts to uh two of them got up to
like literally a half a billion dollars
approximately. Uh and they didn't do
that by by keeping the risk down to a
fraction of 1% per day, you know. So
they had a much bigger risk appetite
which uh led to some significant draw
downs along the way. But it also made it
possible for them to get to the
spectacular uh uh amount of money they
made. So again, you have to have the
right attitude about risk to do it that
way. And and the one who the trader who
never had a losing month, he would not
be he couldn't trade that way. He asked
the guy to keep it super and he he
doesn't hold positions. He does not hold
positions overnight either. So again,
different personalities, different
psycholog psychologies, different
talents, different interests, different
beliefs, etc., etc., etc. So, which
means that you you to be successful,
you've got to find the approach that
works for you.
>> Yeah, it may like what I'm hearing is
maybe you don't necessarily have to
look, you need to look within, you know,
you need to look within because a lot
start out and they want to look
outwardly or try to emulate somebody
else. But a couple things I want to
touch on there. George, you had written
this in in the book as well. You said
there's two types of profitable traders
and Jack was discussing this as far as
you have those who there was a lot of
volatility on the equity curve but then
you had Mr. Consistency who's just not
not very large draw downs at all. You
said there's two types of traders. Those
who generate
exceptional returns and those who excel
at capital preservation. I was I'm
curious with that. Do you think there's
a way to balance both of those into a
trader or you're one or the other?
>> Um, you know, that was in my preface and
I don't know that the capital
preservation types were really what we
were thinking about with the wizards.
Just to be clear, I was more speaking
about myself. I'm better at protecting
money as opposed to making tons of it.
Uh, can you balance somebody who makes
money? It's funny. I listen to the uh
the reminiscences of a stock operator.
uh audio book on my morning walks and
there's a line and I don't remember the
specifics, the names wouldn't matter
because these guys are a hundred years
dead if they were ever real. But uh the
main character who's essentially
Livermore is saying some people have the
money-making instinct and they often
have big swings. Other people have the
hoarding instinct and sometimes you'll
get people with both and they die
disgustingly rich. So, uh I think
they're out there. I think it's just
rare because for the most part I think
what it takes to have gigantic compound
annual growth rate returns that are also
scalable requires you to take big ups
and downs and that's sort of the
antithesis of let's protect capital that
we got to see these guys returns. They
send us their material to verify and
some of the guys that had the best sort
of results. So their monthly percentage
returns are just they're wild. you look
at them and you think, how did they have
the fortitude to to wake up and trade
the next month because it was a down 30
or 50% month. Um, so anyway, to your
question, I'm sure some exist, but I
think it's tough. People tend to usually
either be in a make tons of money and
experience lots of volatility better at
protecting.
Just to be clear, there's shades of
gray. So, if you think of Jason Barry,
who you interviewed, he has almost no
down lines at all. So that's
exceptional. And and Rick Bandazian is
the other one. Yeah.
>> We really never have down months. These
guys are like cash registers. It's like
having a WT.
>> I know. It's it's incredible. But then
you'll have those that take $5,000 and
turn it into what a hundred million. I
mean, high volatility. Um
>> Kevin, I would say there were I think in
in this last book as well as in the
previous market wizard books, there are
people who kind of blended. uh they do
they do very well. I'll give one example
of his current book uh Lance Brightstein
um I mean well he was a prop firm
originally trading started out with
small amounts but then went on to trade
left at after 10 years and traded his
own account but ultimately ended up like
at 100 million and along the way I don't
believe he had any large draw downs. He
certainly wasn't making money every
month uh uh like some of the a couple of
the other guys, but he made a ton more
money. So, uh I think there are people
who kind of blended blended the two.
They they didn't make really good sums
of money and still had reasonable draw
downs.
>> Or do you think even too as they get
older? Is it Ed Dakota um that says
there are those who are bold and those
who are old, but you're you can't blend
the old and bold together?
Is that the one?
>> That's a typical Dakota line, man.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So, with u today's the the
young traders you guys have have
interviewed,
do you think that there's a certain edge
that may exist in today's I guess the
landscape of today that I mean certainly
didn't exist back with the original
market wizards where with technology and
access maybe the speed. Do you think can
you identify certain edges?
>> You know, I I don't know if the edges
have changed. I mean, they're always
different. Um, I I think of a couple of
traders in this book who, let's say,
made good use of uh 13D reports, you
know, really really getting into the
thick thick of it and and finding
situations where they had information,
not information that is available to the
public. It's just the public doesn't dig
into it like they did. And uh so
I but that existed all along. It's just
you know in this case some of these
traders that's type of information that
was instrumental in making their initial
millions. So uh I wouldn't say it's so
much a result of technology. Uh I mean
the technology comes in of course
naturally uh you're going to review a
thousand charts or something like that.
It wouldn't have been practical uh when
you had to chart them by paper or
something like that. So that's that's a
consequence of just technology, but it's
nothing unique really. It's uh I think
that would have been true for for 20
years now.
>> And George, do you think with the the
three principles you've laid out, do you
think they apply in a like a AIdriven
world? Do you think they apply
universally?
>> I do. I mean, there's exceptions. Chris
Camilillo from Unknown Market Wizards
didn't use
really cut his losses. Although I read
his book and he bought options. So in
theory, he's limiting his risk in some
capacity. But I think it's uh the
principles are more the rule than the
exception. And one thing I found from
from studying all of the traders and
doing these interviews is there are
always going to be exceptions. There's
always going to be almost every rule.
But I I think for me personally and for
the masses, we would probably be better
served to find out what's more common
and more prevalent and go with that
because the exceptions are the
exceptions, right? Um so yeah.
>> Did did you think that when going
through all the the wizards over the
years, Jack, do do you think there's
that traders have to experience
losses, draw downs? Even in this book
there were some level of uh you know
blowups of early accounts. Can can a
trader start their journey and just kind
of smooth sail or do they need do they
have to learn those three principles
George points out to respect the trend
to cut your losses? Let your winners
run. Is that something that's learned or
is it more like innate? Well, it's well,
first of all, some the there the number
of these market wizards who obviously by
there being in a book have performed
spectacularly well. Um the number of
them that experienced early failures in
in many cases multi complete failure,
complete blowouts and in some cases
multiple complete blowouts is is much
higher than one would think. So uh that
that is true. Uh however not all not all
of them had that experience. I think um
there there are number of ones who were
successful kind of out the bat never had
a really um really really like I think
Michael Platt of Blueest is a good
example of that. I think he was just
successful from the beginning and just
never had that experience. But that's
the exception. I mean there for the most
part most of them did experience some
some episode early on that was uh that
was a if not a wipeout completely a draw
down that took them to the edge. Uh for
example, Paul Tudtor Jones never
literally completely wiped out, but as I
tell the story in in uh market the
original market wizards, uh he had one
trade uh where he literally after doing
quite well literally lost twothirds of
his assets on one trade in a few days.
Uh and he did come to the brink of
quitting. Um he just they it could have
gone either way. there might not have
been a ball to the Jones of that we
know. Uh so [clears throat] so it was a
very close call. So even if they didn't
blow out completely, most of them did
experience some traumatic trade early on
or along the way. There are a few
exceptions.
>> Can I chime in on that for a sec? Um
>> Phil Geter, if I pronounced his name
right. To me personally, it's probably
one of the closest things I've ever seen
to a natural-born trader, if there is
such a thing. And there's just something
in his mindset. He w he still wiped out
twice. So, so let's keep that in mind
before he went on to to huge success.
But his mindset was just this isn't
working. I should stop. And you for me
as a trader, not that I'm a market
wizard, I'm not, but it took years to
get to that level. And I think for a lot
of people it takes months or or years if
they ever do it. So the fact that he got
there very quickly I just found
interesting and I think it was just
inherently the way his mind thinks about
things that sort of differed from most
other people. So but even the guys that
I believe are sort of born with a a
temperament that's suited to the
principles still lose money early on for
whatever that's worth.
>> Yeah. So with with the next generation
here, is was there any interview in
there that that you think challenged
your own kind of beliefs or maybe
thoughts at all?
>> Yeah, I mean the idea of the idea of
shorting smaller cap stocks as a way to
get success would certainly not have
been on my list of on my top 100 list of
ways to [laughter]
market.
>> And you George.
>> Yeah, I would agree. I I talk about the
the trading literature or scripture
since I read so much about trading. And
if somebody came and said, "Hey, I got
this great idea on how to make money.
We're going to short small caps for day
trades and we're going to make a
fortune." I just said, "Hey, you read it
wrong. You're not supposed to do that."
So the fact that not one but multiple of
them made a lot of money doing that was
very surprising and kind of taught me
that there's there was another guy too
um who made a bunch of money in
agriculture and I had never really seen
anybody make a lot of money in
agriculture
>> and so those two things in particular it
was like these are things that I thought
maybe weren't impossible but close and
yet here they are succeeding at it. So
the the exercise of writing the book and
doing the interviews was certainly eye
opening and taught me that there's
probably somebody out there doing
something that you don't think is po
possible and they're doing it very well.
>> Yeah. Go
>> mentioned the trader. This is
interesting. The trader he's talking
about the A. Uh this is one of the two
guys who got to around a half a billion
and uh he literally made his early for
you know early years first four five six
years uh trading not not only a futures
but a future spreads so you know if you
told me somebody's going to start out
with with a you know uh well he he had
save I think he did in this case he did
save up $7 million that he made while he
was trading for a prop firm. So, but if
you could tell me that somebody was
going to parlay that into a half billion
uh and trading agricultural future
spreads uh predominantly until the later
years, I would have not thought that
made would be possible.
>> Yeah, that's that's incredible. U so
with this the next generation here, what
what was the criteria, if you will? Uh
did did they need to be under 40? What
what was the criteria when it's like
who's who's going to be in the the next
generation?
>> Yeah. Age wasn't a criteria. Uh it was a
preference. Uh
>> yeah. Yeah.
>> We came across somebody who was
absolutely perfect but didn't fit the
age. So I I think the oldest guy turned
50 uh after we we did the interview. So
uh if you were going strictly by keeping
people in their 30s and 40s um it would
not have been possible. Then of course
since we're looking for people with
track records of at least 10 years,
there's a limit to how young they can
be. Although I think at least one trader
was in the 20s though. Uh so um so age
wasn't the criteria. It like it it was
no different than all the other market
wizard books. There are two ways
somebody gets chosen. One they take a
relatively moderate amount of money and
turn into a large fortune. That's always
a good story.
>> And two is they have phenomenal return
risk. So yeah, the two people in the
book who have this, you know, almost
even no losing months or almost no
losing months, their returns are not in
terms of dollars are not spectacular by
any means, but the fact that they just
turn the markets into a money machine
that they live off of, that's the story.
So it's one of those.
>> Wow, that's incredible. And George, your
thoughts on that?
>> We didn't set out to write this book. So
it's
>> they just kind of came to you. Is that
what you say? they just kind of came to
you.
>> Well, you know, um, so we, and this is
in the preface, people can pre-order now
and get the first two prefaces in the
first chapter, but we're going to write
a second book that's going to come out
in about a year and a half, two years,
something like that. And when we
originally started doing interviews, we
were focused on hedge fund guys as well.
So, we um ultimately decided that we
were going to do this book on
independent traders, most of whom wound
up being younger. And then the second
book is going to be hedge fund guys. But
essentially because of that it's not
like we said hey let's set out and let's
find traders who are under 50 who have
achieved great things.
>> So it just sort of worked out when
sifting through the big volume of
different people that we were looking
at. And as I said earlier the original
idea wasn't even to write a wizards
book. It was early struggle. So it it it
kind of evolved. One thing Jack told me
is that the wizards books are sort of
Jack, correct me if I'm paraphrasing
this wrong, but they're like a dragon
and you're riding the dragon and you're
kind of steering it, but it's kind of
going where it goes. If you want to
speak to that, Jack, but it's uh
>> Yeah, I mean, basically, that's right.
>> So, so yeah, it kind of evolves and it
becomes what it becomes throughout the
process. So, we didn't set out and say
we're looking to capture traders that
are plus or minus 25 to 30 and and
that's it. It just went that way over
time.
>> Got it. Got it. What What do you think
that the the young people in this book
have that impresses you or maybe they do
really well at that some of maybe some
older market wizards don't don't do
well? I mean, is there something that
you can see with the younger generation
where they really succeed?
>> I think it's still the same things as my
books. take uh quite a majority of them
are super hard workers. Uh
>> the fault of in my mind not the way I
want to live want to live my life. uh uh
the the fellow of no losing months uh
gets up at like 4:30 a.m. to check the
the pre-market situation and uh his last
look at the markets is around 8:00 p.m.
Yeah, he takes a couple of breaks during
the day, but that's you know that's
that's your life in front of the screen.
So uh that's an example of hard work but
it's by no means the only one that uh
that I mean you read this book and you
will see that a number of these traders
just
lived uh market analysis and trading. I
mean their life was that was their life.
They just they just were constantly
researching and uh constantly working
and including weekends including
holidays. uh um and they would come in
they would if they they worked at a prop
shop they would even come in on weekends
uh to sort of go over their trades and
so there was no there was very little
free time and sometimes no vacations and
so this this this hard work ethic was
very prominent in this book but it's
been there from the very first book as
well. So, do you think there needs to be
a level of of passion? That's a common
theme I've heard in a lot of the
interviews. Like a lot of these guys who
succeed in this industry, they have
passion. Um,
>> this has to be this has to be something
you really enjoy and and you get that
you get that message from these people.
It's not that, you know, they're they're
doing all this work and it's trudger,
you know, it's drudgery. Even if it's
going through, you know, 13D reports,
which would not be most people's idea of
a fun time, but for them it's like a
treasure hunt on finding the pieces of
information. And so, yeah, to to have
that type of devotion, to be willing to
commit that much energy and time and a
large chunk of your life to this, you
have to actually love the the actual
endeavor. It's not about the money. I
mean they may in in some cases people
are motivated to to get into markets
because it seems like a path to possible
fortunes but but to succeed and what
ultimately happens in the process is
they find they love this thing and they
just it's like their work is their
hobby. It has to be that type of
attitude. If you're only in it if if
doing all that research is work uh
you're not going to be you're not going
to succeed spectacularly. And that's
your experience too, George, right? I
mean, your hobby is is your work, vice
versa. And was that your experience with
um the market wizards as well?
>> Yeah.
>> Jack made me think of a Ed Sakakota
quote, which I think came from the first
book, but it's uh great traders don't
have the talent, the talent has them,
which I think is pretty accurate. And
this is this is I think what these guys
while they're trading some of them are
walking away from it but um while
they're trading it's really what they're
living for. And it's you know people say
like god country core I think trading
would be very high up on their hierarchy
of priorities in life if you were to ask
them.
>> Wow. Yeah. So what's a what do you think
there's there's a critical quality
amongst the market wizards. What what is
it that one quality that you think of
off the top of your head stands out to
you, Jack? What's that quality that they
possess?
>> There are a few exceptions, very few. Uh
but if you had to name the single most
important unifying theme, it would be
risk management. So not the methodology,
not the trading, not the research, but
risk management. I I would say if you
asked every person I've interviewed what
is the most important thing about
trading, I would put money on the single
answer that would turn up the most would
be risk management.
>> Okay. I want to follow up on that, but
George, go ahead.
>> I thought you were asking more about
their personality traits as opposed to
trading methods. So maybe I
misunderstood your question.
>> Yeah, go either direction. Give us one
of each. I think if you're thinking of
personality traits, I have a list that
uh is in the book and I have it here,
but I don't think it's um one thing. It
reminds me of another Sakola quote. I'm
like a parrot of Sakakota, but a lot of
what he says is is true. But somebody
said, "What's the most important part of
a trading system?" And he said, "I don't
view a single part as the most important
just as what's more important, your
liver, your heart, or your spleen." I
mean, uh, so I think they all function
together, but these guys and and prior
wizards have a lot of sort of common
personality traits, and I could go
through them if you'd like or you tell
me.
>> Yeah, go for it. Well, I had that quote
here, too. It's fascinating. There's no
best car. There's no best spouse. It
depends on the individual. And, uh,
Sakakota also has right here about the
only one thing is for sure is that there
isn't a sure thing. I mean, he he was
brilliant. I mean, with the quotes and
um just absolutely
brilliant guy, but go for it, George.
Yeah, let's dive into that a little bit.
>> I guess the same way that the principles
are inherent to most wizards, there's
always exceptions, but they're
personality things, and they are one is
they're they're usually pretty
self-aware. They understand who they are
and what they want. Two is they have
clear goals. They're not confused about
what they're trying to achieve. Three is
they believe in themselves. Um, a lot of
times they believe in themselves when
there is no evidence to support that
belief whatsoever. Whether that's blown
up trading accounts or family members
telling them you're not good at this, go
do something else. Uh, four is that they
are pretty independent as people. You're
not going to probably find them working
a 9 to5 as a a cog in the machine. Um,
five, they're very passionate about
trading as we mentioned a minute or two
ago. Six, they're committed. they're
they're sticking with this through thick
or thin. So that leads to persistence.
They're all very persistent in achieving
their goals. Uh beyond that, they're
they're very willing to pursue their
dreams despite the fear of failure. So
they press on even if they're afraid
they might fail. And they really have an
ability to focus uh that you don't see
so much in everyday people. So I think
those as far as my research are the most
common personality traits of really
traders, market wizards or or other.
>> Jack, your thoughts?
>> Yeah, I mean I would also I mean there
there are quite a number of others but
one I think that is really critical and
I think it's true of just about uh all
market wizards is they have flexibility
uh in their thinking. uh they're not
tied to the idea. I mean, yes, they put
on a they I what is the u I'm trying to
think Peter Brent has a good way of
putting it. Um and um uh I I'm
forgetting the phrase exactly now, but
>> I think I remember it's
>> strong opinions weakly held.
>> Yeah, that's it. Strong opinions weakly
held. See, George knew it just from the
vague description I was giving. uh
that's exactly the the the the key to
it. So uh they uh they have an idea,
they really believe in it, they put on a
trade, but if the market action or news
or whatever dictates that the idea is
wrong, uh they're quite quite able to to
abandon it. Uh they don't continue to
hope. uh they're they have this uh
incredible flexibility to to change
including going the other way. So you'll
find a number of stories in the market
wizard books where where a trader
thought one way and then comes up
repeatedly and then ends up going
realizing they're wrong and doing the
exact opposite and that being one of the
best trades they've ever had. They wow.
>> So that becomes that's a common that's a
common occurrence. So this is very very
important and that's why a lot of people
just by their psych [snorts]
psychological makeup would make uh would
not would not make good traders. Uh so
because they're not willing to admit
they're wrong when they're wrong.
>> So remaining unbiased, you know,
objective. That's what I wanted to touch
on with you, Jack. This you said strong
opinion, weakly held. And you were
speaking on fundamentals earlier and I I
had heard you in another interview. It
really resonated me when you said this
you because you had started out of
course when you your journey with you
you started out more fundamental because
that was your background at that time
but then you said you kind of went like
you started to lean towards technicals
and the reason for that which I want you
to dive into is like you think about
like a company you're saying you have a
strong opinion or a company has great
intrinsic value and it to you almost to
the trader it feels like well I'm
getting a better bargain price so you
can just constantly add add uh as the as
the value you know drops because in your
mind well this is going to gravitate
towards that intrinsic value over time
and be worth more. What are your I want
to hear your story and your thoughts on
that fundamentals, risk management tied
to technicals versus
>> Exactly. That's exactly and I think it's
a very important point and it's not I
want to preface it here by saying that
I'm not knocking fundamentals. I'm just
stating what I think are is the reality
of the structure of the markets. Uh and
there are plenty of people I've
interviewed who used only fundamentals
were very successful. However,
fundamental analysis by its very nature
is almost difficult to um to risk
management. So, as you kind of alluded
because you talked about it. So, you
have a company, let's say a company's
trading at $50 and and you're you go
through for fundamentals and this
company should be worth $80, right? So,
you go long at 50 looking for it to go
at 80, let's say. Okay. Uh then it goes
down to 45 for 40. Uh nothing has
changed fundamentally, but it's down to
40. So hey, if [clears throat] it was a
good price, if the fundamentals said it
was worth 80, now you know when it's 40
instead of 50, it's an even better
upside potential. So the the irony is
with pure fundamental analysis if
nothing fundamentally changes the more
the market goes against you the more you
should want to put on which is exact
opposite of risk management. Whereas
most if not almost all technical
analysis if the market goes against you
it sort of automatically negates the
reason for being in the trade. If take a
very simple example, if you're a trend
follower and you know market breaks out
on the upside and you go long or the
market has a crossover or whatever and
you go long then if it goes against you
that crossover goes the other way the
breakout turns out to be a false
breakout. The the the methodology itself
argues that you're wrong but fundamental
analysis exactly opposite. So there's a
built-in difficulty with that. And so
from my own experience I found that
because of that it was very difficult
for me to use fundamental analysis
because I had no way of telling you you
know when to get out and when I started
using chart analysis uh and this is a
this is kind of I remember people ask me
sometimes what was your best trade
and it's never it's not a trade and I
think back my best trade I remember back
a trade way back when I just early and
then you know just started trading very
small amounts of money but when I
started this was when I switched over to
chart analysis and I remember it was the
back then it was the D mark it wasn't
the euro and uh the euro didn't come on
for decades later um and uh the D mark
had sort of had a long slide had gone
into like a six-month base it looked
like a bottom and sort of I kind of
looked at that I said yeah you know kind
of this should be enough and it's been
building a base and I kind of anticip
ipated would break out on the upside. So
I went long and I put a stop in like you
know 15 20 ticks below the low of the
base and then one day the market went
down sharply hit my stop I was knocked
out and then the great thing was that
after that for the next few weeks it
just kept on going down and that is that
I always think back is kind of my best
trade because I I was dead wrong. I lost
only a small amount of money and if I
hadn't had you know the risk management
it would have been a large loss. So uh
that's like a personal example.
>> Ever watch a stock rip and think I could
have nailed that if I had real capital.
The truth is many capable traders never
reach their potential. Not due to lack
of skill but lack of scale. Trade the
pool was built to solve exactly that. A
firm designed for serious individuals
who want access to the US equity markets
with meaningful buying power up to
$200,000 without committing their own
capital. Get access to virtually every
stock and ETF. Go long or short freely
with the flexibility professional
traders expect. You're evaluated on one
thing, your ability to manage risk and
execute with consistency. Meet the
standard and you trade at scale. No
subscriptions, no ongoing commitments.
Whether you're still refining your
strategy, a trader with experience who
hasn't yet broken through, or a seasoned
professional simply looking for more
capital, trade the pool is built to meet
you where you are and take you that next
step further. The markets have evolved.
Access has evolved. Now, so has the way
traders operate within them. Trade the
pool. I love that because I mean, the
best trade you're thinking of is is that
that is the loser, not necessarily what
most would think is the winner. Um,
George, do you have a take on that? The
fundamentals versus technical risk
management applied.
>> Yeah, I mean, I don't want to repeat
what Jack just said, but I I agree
mostly with what he said. Actually,
Kelvin uh in the book, Kelvin Chu, he
says essentially the same. He says that
fundamentals can be helpful, but they
have no risk management. So, I think
that's the right take. you if you're a
fundamental guy and it drops logically
you should buy more if the reasons you
own it haven't changed so but what do
you do if it just keeps going down and I
guess people could limit their risk by
saying position sizing but that opens a
whole can of worms of sort of Wall
Street versus Lal Street how do you look
at risk how do you size positions and
probably more than we want to get into
today so I'll support what Jack said
>> do yeah I'd like to add sort of to be
fair here I was thinking the other side
while George was answering. So about on
the fundamentals like think of a pure
fundamental one of the pure
fundamentalist I I interviewed
predominantly pure fundamentalist Martin
Taylor who started out as an emerging um
market type of uh stock trader and
eventually uh branched out to also trade
uh uh trade uh regular larger cap
stocks. Um but so I I remember when I
interviewed him uh and he but just
enormously successful. He he built his
various funds into about seven eight
billion and decided to give the money
back because he didn't want to bother
investors and just kept a billion of his
own money and a few clients or friends
that he allowed in. Anyway, so at the
time I interviewed him u and he was a
trader just to put to give the context
he was a trader who um a bad draw down
for him would be like high teens teens
those were like his worst draw downs and
at the time I interviewed him
interestingly he was in one of those
draw downs and he had he had one
position uh on that was responsible for
most of the draw down and he was long he
was long Apple u at that time before the
circuit splits I think it was like maybe
350 going down to 350 or something like
that. And um he was so convinced on the
fundamentals and he he like say he was a
pure fundamentalist and he really did
his work. But to him it was clear as
could be that Apple could have to would
have to go up because uh he at that this
was back in 2012 and he kind of foresaw
that the earnings the the forward
earnings that people were projecting
were basically based on their growth in
largely US and so forth was not taking
account that Apple was going to explode
globally particularly in China and other
places and uh he saw that those
estimates were just woefully fully
inadequate relative to to the true
global growth Apple was going to see. So
not only he was not concerned about that
opposition at all. I think he might have
even been adding. So that sounds like
the antithesis of of uh of risk
management in a way it is. But the only
way he controlled that is by limiting
the the position to a certain
percentage. I think the extreme percent
he would put in the position would have
been Apple at that time which might have
been around 15%. So he had to be, you
know, it's not going to go to zero. So
he has to just keep his risk manager.
The idea, well, this one position, I
really totally believe in it. Uh, I've
got 15% of my money in it, but it's not
going to go to zero. It's not even going
to go down 50%. So the position can only
lose a certain percentage from that
realistically, and I'm willing to hold
it. That that's the way he achieved the
risk match. And by the way, six months
after that interview, I think Apple had
maybe even doubled. It had just gone. He
was totally he was 100% right. He was
also incidentally short rim at the same
time. The Blackberry company
>> rim at the time was 50. And I remember
these things, you know, eventually went
went
uh I believe. Uh so, you know, you
that's a long and a short and completely
convinced of both and you know, couldn't
be more right. Well, it sounds like you
just need to have a high level of
conviction, right?
>> Yeah. Yes. I'm g that. Yeah. I don't
want to come off sounding like you can't
use fundamentals. There are, you know,
here's an example of a guy that does
fundamentals uh doesn't have risk
management of a sense of we typically
talk about it, but he achieves it
through limiting the position to certain
a certain maximum amount of his
portfolio.
>> Well, it comes back to this quote I've
heard you say, Jack, which the 10 words
of advice. Do you want to say uh it's
just knowing where you're getting out
before you get in and if you know that
you know fundamentally or technically I
mean that you're going to be managing
risk, right? Um so one of the quotes
that came to mind too in regards to this
was William O'Neal. So he said the
secret to winning is not being right all
the time. It's losing the least amount
of money when wrong. Uh love that quote.
So, George, I wanted to ask both of you
uh really, but just if you can think
back on all the interviews from the next
generation, is there just the most
memorable moment for you in it?
>> There's something in this there's a
number of things in this book which
haven't in many other books Mark before,
but one of them is an anonymous
interview. I did. In another case, we'll
have an interview where uh if you want
to get an attention, we can, but I ended
up not being able to use the interview.
Uh but I kind of pleaded or just asked
the uh trader if I could just use one
little section. So, which he agreed to
and it's like two pages uh called Trader
X or something like that. So, I did have
a little snippet of an anonymous
interview, but I never had a full
interview, an anonymous uh in in the
book. And uh in this book, we do have
one because uh the story is so
spectacular and so compelling and
interesting. And I figured, look, uh
nobody would know if I had his real
name, nobody would know him anyway
because he's completely under the radar
and he's just a private individual,
right? So, nobody would know. So, what
what difference does a name make? It's a
story that counts. Uh it's, you know,
the story is accurate. The story is
true. And and uh this is this is a
fellow who u was a musician and uh was
in one of the country's top music
schools and uh dropped out then found
discovered he passionate about music but
then discovered trading. he was
passionate about trading and decided and
dropped out like a year before he
graduated uh from music conservatory uh
to just focus on trading and uh the
story goes on from there and it's uh uh
he ends he's one of the two people who
who kind of got to that near half
billion mark. So, uh, that that is to me
that story to me was the it's it's also
if not the longest chapter in any market
wizard book, uh, it's close. I think
Mark Marcus was a very long chapter, but
it's it's up there in one of the longest
chapters ever because the story is very
interesting. has a lot of ups and downs
and um and he ends up with a philosophy
that I find quite interesting uh which
is looking to ba basically give back
money uh for his various philanthropies.
>> Was it challenging to get that interview
or was he reluctant at all?
>> He was clearly well for one thing kind
of had his lawyer draw up like a
ninepage document which we
[clears throat] had to change.
>> Oh wow.
Yeah,
>> incredible.
>> You know, for the for the secrecy I'm
>> uh I thought of mine um just sorry it
took me a minute to think of it, but
Lance, who's chapter 2, he was
describing one of his mentors, and I
don't want to name this guy, but he
talked about the guy and where he had
worked and where he had gone to college
and he had lived in Asia. And as he's
describing this guy, I'm like, I know
this guy. I sat next to this guy for
five years. So at one of our breaks I
said, "Was this this guy?" And he's
like, "Yeah." And it was like, "Holy
smokes, small world." You know, we
>> the guy that was his mentor is the guy
that I sat next to for 5 years. So that
was probably the biggest uh coincidence
and that's memorable thing from the
>> the book in terms of just came to mind
right now.
>> Well, you [sighs and gasps] both have
studied elite performers uh over the
years and it's led us to this book. I'm
so excited for it. Been uh reading it
myself. It's incredible. It u comes out
June 9th uh 2026 here. Well, I wanted to
ask too, George, because you got a lot
of really great papers out out there.
Where can they find your work, George?
>> I think the best place to start is to go
to X, formerly Twitter. Uh my handle is
GFC4,
and I've got a link tree there that
links to a lot of the different things
I'm doing, including the the papers and
other materials and the book. So that's
the best place I think to go to find the
central hub for for George.
>> Okay, perfect. And then of course you
guys are already working on the next uh
market wizards book. Is that correct?
>> No, we didn't start yet, but uh
>> haven't started. So what happened as
George said before we had uh too much
material for one book and sort of
thought about well how do we divide them
in a lot some logical way and the most
logical way seemed to be solo traders
versus hedge funds and so we've had a
few of these hedge fund uh interviews
that we've done uh and uh we'll
obviously have to do more to fill out
that book but we have you know uh I
don't know a third or a half of the
potential raw material
there. Uh, in some cases, we've actually
written chapters. In the other cases,
we've got the interview, which hasn't
been transformed yet into chapters.
Well, Jack, every time you think it's
the last market wizards book, there's
another one on the way. So, maybe we'll
get another what, five or six more
over the next 10 to 20 years or so. So,
hey gentlemen, this has been excellent.
I mean, just last words over to you
guys. What's if someone for for the
person reading this book, you know,
what's one lesson you really want them
to to grab from this book when reading
it? Start with you, Jack.
>> Well, uh I'm going to be unconventional
here. uh let's take it kind of in the
opposite direction is one thing you'll
see in this book is that a number of
these traders ca ultimately came to the
conclusion that as a successful they've
been that they just didn't want to even
though they continue to churn out money
just by and it seems like a loss not to
keep trading because they're not trading
or devoting time to other things is
going to take away from their making uh
highly likely making more money. uh they
still decide that they want to use their
life in some other direction. They've
done the trading bit. They've been
successful. They got more money than
they need to live on for the rest of
their lives. They want to do something
else. So, uh you know, I think an
important lesson is there's more to life
than trading. I mean, as long as it's
your passion, what you want to do, go
for it. But keep in mind that that's not
all of life. and uh you for your
whatever your case may be uh that may
not be the direction you necessarily
want to go or if you've gone that way
you may not want to stay that way. So I
think it's important to have overall
perspective there's more to life than
trading.
And over to you, George.
>> If you incorporate the consistent
principles into your process, whether
it's discretionary or systematic, I
think you have a much greater chance of
survival and [clears throat]
and that's what it's about. So, I would
say find a way to cut your losses uh as
you learn and you'll save your money.
You won't lose it all.
>> Cut your losses and stick with the
principles.
>> Stick with the principles. Uh I love it.
That's a consistent theme here. And also
something I took away from the interview
as well is there's no singular approach.
I mean so many of these market wizards
had different approaches and found their
own success while sticking to George's
three principles. So thank you so much
for coming on. I mean the the market
wizards timeless material that's going
to live on for generations. Um and
hopefully this video as well that
traders can go back and watch and learn
from. So again, thank you Jack, thank
you George so much for taking the time.
Thanks again.
>> You've reached the end of this episode
of Chat with Traders, but rest assured,
there are more episodes loaded with real
market insight and zero hype on the way
soon. So, to stay updated [music] with
each great new release, subscribe to the
podcast, and we'd love it if you'd leave
a rating and review. We'll catch you
next time on Chat with Traders.
>> [music]